Finding Aid for Mu Phi Epsilon. Gamma Chapter (University of Michigan) records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Mu Phi Epsilon. Gamma Chapter (University of Michigan) records 1945-1995, 2011
Mu Phi Epsilon. Gamma Chapter (University of Michigan)
9 oversize volumes
2 oversize folders
1 linear foot
2011066 Bimu F41 2
Gamma Chapter at University of Michigan of Mu Phi Epsilon, established in 1904, part of professional music sorority. In 1976 membership opened to males. Organization is still active. Material includes minutes, correspondence, membership records, financial records, and scrapbooks.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (donor no. 10545) was received from Gamma Chapter of Mu Phi Epsilon in May 2011. May 2011.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Mu Phi Epsilon was founded in 1903 as a professional music sorority and has since become an international fraternity. The Gamma chapter of Mu Phi Epsilon was created in Ann Arbor in 1904, becoming the third chapter of the organization. Its mission is the advancement of music both nationally and internationally, the promotion of musicianship and scholarship, the fostering of loyalty to the alma mater, and the development of lasting friendships. Membership is based on scholarship, musicianship, character, and personality.
In addition to regular meetings and initiation activities, the Gamma Chapter of Mu Phi Epsilon also provides performance opportunities for its members. The chapter has hosted other musicians and offered lectures over the years, and has also provided music therapy at local hospitals. Another responsibility of the organization is attendance in Mu Phi Epsilon's district and international conferences.
The Gamma Chapter of Mu Phi Epsilon was originally founded as a sorority, but with the enactment of Title IX, it became coed. Membership was anywhere from twenty to fifty members during the 1950s and 1960s, but in the mid 1970s, the chapter membership averaged between ten and twenty. During this time, the chapter was placed on probation for several years as it struggled to carry out its responsibilities. Gamma Chapter remains active today.
The chapter is comprised of officers and members, a faculty adviser, and patronesses. The chapter also cooperates with the Ann Arbor Alumni Chapter of Mu Phi Epsilon and other sororities and fraternities in hosting events for its members and the public.
The records for the Gamma Chapter of Mu Phi Epsilon contain minutes, correspondence, membership records, financial records, scrapbooks, and nationally published materials. These records are divided into Administrative, Membership, Correspondence, Publications, and Scrapbooks. The earliest records date from 1945, leaving the first 40 years of the chapter undocumented. Materials are arranged in chronological order, starting with most recent date except where noted.
Subjects:
Greek letter societies--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Music--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.; University of Michigan. School of Music.
Genre Terms:
Scrapbooks.
- Administrative
  The Administrative series, 1945-1995, contains minutes, reports from officers, financial reports, and governance information. The minutes document meetings, decisions, activities and events, and membership in Gamma Chapter, and are complete between 1945 and 1959; gaps appear throughout the remaining years. Presidents' reports contain regular reports created by the chapter president for the national leadership of Mu Phi Epsilon and presidential speeches to Gamma members, which report on the status and activities of the chapter. Reports from other officers regarding the fulfillment of their duties are included in the Officers' reports, along with reports created by district leadership for national and chapter leaders. The series also includes available are the available annual financial reports for Gamma Chapter. Finally, the series contains materials pertaining to governance, such as Gamma Chapter bylaws, the national constitution and bylaws and officer manuals, from before and after Title IX legislation, and a rushing manual, used in initiation activities.
  - Collegiate Chapter Officers Manual 1963, 1974, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Constitution and Bylaws 1954-1992 (Box 1)
  - Financial Reports 1947-1957 (Box 1)
  - Ledger, unknown start date-1973 (Box 1)
  - Minutes 1945-1993, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Officers Reports 1956-1990 (Box 1)
  - Presidents Reports 1948-1992, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Rushing Manual (dates unknown) (Box 1)
- Membership
  The Membership series, 1951-1993, 2011, contains rosters and officer lists for the chapter. It includes directories and newsletters for the Ann Arbor Alumni chapter, which often worked with the Gamma Chapter in planning and hosting events. It also includes a guest book used during initiation activities.
  - Ann Arbor Alumni Chapter 1955-1993 (Box 1)
  - Guest Book 1969-1983 (Box 1)
  - Membership Records 1951-1993, 2011 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  Correspondence, 1952-1993, is made up of letters to members, other chapters, and District and National officers. Of note is correspondence between national and chapter leaders during the chapter's time on probation. Letters have been arranged chronologically starting with earliest dated material.
  - General 1952-1993 (Box 1)
- Publications
  Publications, 1951-1988, are comprised of issues of Mu Phi Epsilon's national publication The Triangle, as well as other national level publications, that mention the Gamma Chapter, its activities, or its members.
  - National Publications 1951-1988 (Folder 1)
  - National Publications 1951-1988 (Folder 2)
    (continued)
- Scrapbooks
  Scrapbooks, 1949-1981, include candid and formal photographs, taken at various chapter events. Photographs of pledging events are generally included. The scrapbooks also contain documents such as concert programs, newspaper clippings, and event invitations, demonstrating the various activities that Gamma Chapter and its members were involved in.
  - Scrapbook 1 1949-1953 (Volume 1)
  - Scrapbook 2 1956-1957 (Volume 2)
  - Scrapbook 3 1957-1958 (Volume 3)
  - Scrapbook 4 1957-1963 (Volume 4)
  - Scrapbook 5 1967-1969 (Volume 5)
  - Scrapbook 6 1969-1970 (Volume 6)
  - Scrapbook 7 1970-1973 (Volume 7)
  - Scrapbook 8 1976-1979 (Volume 8)
  - Scrapbook 9 1979-1981 (Volume 9)